<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The vvalls of Ierico razed down to the ground. Or, An answer to a lying book, called the Quaking principles dashed in peices [sic]: wherein one called Henoch Howett, which goes under the name of an Anabahtist [sic], doth falsely accuse, and maliciously belye us; his seven principles which he calls ours, I shall lay down, and what we own is vindicated, and what he hath belyed the truth in, is turned upon his own head. / By one who is zealous for the name of the Lord of Hostes, called Edward Burrough.</title>
            <author>Burrough, Edward, 1634-1662.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1654</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 47 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A77972</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B6056A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R170173</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">45578203</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 45578203</idno>
            <idno type="VID">172154</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A77972)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 172154)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2616:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The vvalls of Ierico razed down to the ground. Or, An answer to a lying book, called the Quaking principles dashed in peices [sic]: wherein one called Henoch Howett, which goes under the name of an Anabahtist [sic], doth falsely accuse, and maliciously belye us; his seven principles which he calls ours, I shall lay down, and what we own is vindicated, and what he hath belyed the truth in, is turned upon his own head. / By one who is zealous for the name of the Lord of Hostes, called Edward Burrough.</title>
                  <author>Burrough, Edward, 1634-1662.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 14 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Giles Calvert, and art to be sold, at the Black-Spread-Eagle, at the west-end of Pauls.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1654]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Date of publication suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Friends' Library, London.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Howet, Enoch. --  Quaking principles dashed in pieces.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Apologetic works.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:172154:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE VVALLS OF IERICO Razed down to the GROUND.</p>
            <p>OR, An Anſwer to a lying Book, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Quaking principles daſhed in pei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: Wherein one called <hi>Henoch Howet,</hi> which goes under the name of an ANABAHTIST, doth falſely accuſe, and maliciouſly belye us; his ſeven principles which he calls ours, I ſhall lay down, and what we own is vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated, and what he hath belyed the truth in, is turned upon his own head.</p>
            <p>By one who is zealous for the name of the Lord of hoſtes, called <hi>Edward Burrough.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Giles Calvert,</hi> and art to be ſold, at the <hi>Black-ſpread-Eagle,</hi> at the Weſt-end of <hi>Pauls.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:172154:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:172154:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE VValls of Jerico Razed down to the GROUND.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ow is the time wherein the Lord God of heaven and earth is ſetting up a kingdome, and exalting his name in the earth, and is exalting his own Son up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the holy hill of Sion, and is diſcovering the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of harlots, who hath made all Nations drunk with her fornication, and <hi>Ieſabel</hi> ſhall be caſt into a bed of torment, and the fire of the Lord God is come down from heaven, and is kindled in the earth, to burn up and deſtroy, and to conſume to aſhes, even all thoſe that have worſhipped the Beaſt, and hath his Image, and the falſe Prophets that hath deceived the Nations, and they both ſhall be taken alive, and caſt into the pit; for the Lord is grieved and wearied with this adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſs and viperous generation, who are offering up that which ſtinks in his noſtriles, and ſtrange fire, and are profeſſing him and his reſurrection, who crucifie him, and put him to open ſhame, and they deny the end of his coming, and are offering in <hi>Cains</hi> nature, while they ſlay the Iuſt, and are in the gainſaying of <hi>Corah,</hi> who periſhed in it; and ſo ſhall all thoſe that gainſay the Lord in his way, and now the Lord of heaven and earth is proclaiming war with the Dragon and his Angels, and they ſhall be caſt out, and whoſoever doth reſiſt him in his way, ſhall be broken to pleces as a potters veſſel; and thou <hi>Henoch Howet,</hi> who would limit the holy one of Iſrael, and bind him up in thy carnal reaſon, and ſtint him in his way, and form up things in thy imagination from the Scripture, and walks by tradition; thou art accuſing us among the Papiſts, but let it ſtand for thy ſelf, and to that in thy conſcience I ſpeak, and it will let
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:172154:3"/> thee ſee that all thy worſhip is taken on in thy will, and in that nature, in which the enmity ſtands, and ſo hath taken on things, and up things by tradition from others, and that which was commands to others, who fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed the Lamb whitherſoever he went, and no commands to thee, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth God require thoſe things of that nature, neither doth he accept it, while the bands of wickedneſs is not looſed, and the oppreſſed is not ſet free, and therefore let all fleſh and carnal reaſon be ſilent, for God will confound the wiſdome of the wiſe, and they that have divined in their reaſons, which is in the curſe, and under the curſe, ſhall be mad; now in the day when God is raiſing up his own Image, and bringing back that which hath long been held in captivity, and now the men of the earth, <hi>Pharao,</hi> and all the Inchanters of Egypt, and the Sooth-ſayers, and the Diviners, and <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog,</hi> among which thou <hi>Howet</hi> art found one, and they compaſs the Camp of the Saints about, but fire ſhall come down from heaven, that ſhall deſtroy all the adverſaries of the Lord, and Iſrael ſhall go free.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That which thou cals our firſt principle; And firſt, thou ſaith they oppoſe the word Chriſt, to the written word; and will a word that is a diſcovery ſpiritual to be the word, but whatſoever it is they call the word, it is perfectly falſe, and not the truth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Oh thou lyar and ſlanderer, the Lord will plead with thee, for addars poyſon is under thy tongue, and thou haſt a whores forehead, that art not aſhamed of thy ſelf accuſing, let hundreds in the City of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> who hath heard us, be witneſs againſt thee, and thy lies that thou haſt Printed; and ſuffers them to be cryed up and down the ſtreets, as thy filthy ſongs and ballads, and runs to diſgrace the truth, but to the Lord who is righteous, ſhall thou give an account; and thou art <hi>Ianes</hi> and <hi>Iambres,</hi> that withſtood <hi>Moſes,</hi> and for all thy hard ſpeeches and fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy lyes, ſhall thou give an account, for to him who is the ſearcher of hearts, and that in thy conſcience ſhall bear witneſs againſt thee; and that we oppoſe the word Chriſt to the written word, as thou cals it: I charge it upon thee, that we do not oppoſe Chriſt to the Scripture, for Chriſt is the word, <hi>Iohn</hi> 1. and this the Scripture doth not oppoſe, but bears witneſs to him who is the word, and his name is called the Word of God, and this word became fleſh and dwelt among us, as the Scripture witneſs, and the Word of the Lord endures for ever; but he doth not ſay the Letter endures for ever: but thou that art accuſing that we do not own a form of ſound words, here thou ſhalt be judged out of thy own mouth; where reads thou of a written word in the Scripture? and here thou ſhalt be tryed by the Scripture, and judged by it that thou art a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verter of the Scripture; thou would have more words then one, the word is but one, the word ſanctifies, ſanctifie them through thy word, but he doth not ſay the Letter ſanctifies, and the Word of the Lord is from everlaſting to everlaſting, but the Letter is not from everlaſting; and the Scripture had a beginning, and was declared in time, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie ſhall ceaſe, but the Word is from everlaſting to everlaſting, and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:172154:3" rendition="simple:additions"/> the Word of the Lord is as a hammar, and as a fire, but the Scripture doth not ſay that it is as a hammar and a fire, and yet the word that he ſpoke was ſpirit and life, yet the Scripture is not ſpirit and iife; and thou that would ſet up the letter in the place of God, to try all things, and ſearch all hearts, thou makes an Idol of it, and ſo oppoſes God with it, and ſo would bring that to contend againſt the Lord, the which they witneſs through ſuffering: and I tell thee and all the world, the word is but one, and all who knows God hears that word, and it is a light and a Lanth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horn unto their pathes, but that is inviſible and eternal, and what the Saints were witneſs of this word they declared, 1. <hi>Iohn,</hi> and the Scripture is true, and bears true record and teſtimony of the word, and they were true witneſſes of the word of life that wrote it, and it is a true declaration or teſtimony of thoſe things that are certainly beli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ved, <hi>Luk</hi> 1. of the which they ſaw and heard, and taſted; and all who come to know the Word of the Lord, reads it again, and ſees it as it is written: and further, thy en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy and ſhame is made manifeſt, that thou would accuſe, and yet thou ſaith whatſoever they call the word, it is perfectly falſe, and not truth; here thou would judge, and yet thou cannot tell what we call the Word, but at laſt concludes its falſe whatever it be: and here thou blaſphemes, and cals Chriſt Jeſus in whom is all truth, falſe; for no other word I own but Chriſt, and the Scripture ſpeaks of no word of God but one, and thou that would make the Letter the Word, it ſelf ſhall judge thee; and thou makes much mincing and arguments in thy carnal reaſon, and ſaith the ground of error, is ignorance of the Scripture, and thou brings <hi>Mark</hi> and <hi>Matthew;</hi> alas, I know what <hi>Mark</hi> and <hi>Matthew</hi> wrote is true, if thou had an ear to hear, the ground of all error is becauſe he is not known, nor his voice whom the Scripture bear record of; and thou ſaith we drive men into darkneſs, that works upon people to diſeſteem the Scripture, and perſwades people to an uſleſsneſs of the Scriptures; let all that have heard us in the City of <hi>London,</hi> or elſewhere ſpeak, if they heard us ſay the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture was uſleſs, or did diſeſteem it, but on the contrary we exhorted them to ſearch if the Scripture did not bear witneſs to thoſe things we declared, and ſo let ſhame cover thy face thou falfe accuſer; and thou brings 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.17. that it is for the perfecting the man of God, and that its profitable to correct and inſtruct; this is owned, but its not the man of God, thou would have perfected by it, but ſuch hirelings as thy ſelf hath been, and falſe accuſers as thou art, and I ſay it is profitable to us to reprove thee, and correct thee, and read thy portion; a lyars portion is in the lake, and as <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.4. its not denyed, but as Chriſt Ieſus is witneſſed, who is the Comforter, whlch the Scripture bears witneſs of, there is comfort and hope; and thou ſaith the Scripture proves the New birth, and teacheth perſeverance to the end, it bears teſtimony of ſome that did witneſs the New birth, and that perſevered unto the end; but what is this to thee, that never came one ſtep in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> way,? and as for promiſes, there is no promiſe, but condemnation in the Scripture, in ſuch as thee, and read it, the lyar and falſe accuſer, and the envious ſhall not inhererit the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:172154:4"/> of God, and their own, thy promiſe and thy portion.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Particular which thou cals a miſtake, that is ſpeaking to a thing within thee, I would fain know what can be meant of the thing within men, for there is nothing to be ſpoken to in man, but man.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Here thy igno<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ance, ſhame and envy is made manifeſt, that thou that hath pretended to be a Miniſter, and a Paſtor of a Church, and cannot tell what thou hath ſpoke, to what hath thou miniſtered, to the wind, or haſt thou miniſtered to the devil, and preached glad tid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings to him, who is in the tranſgreſſion, and free grace to him that hath walked contrary to God it is ſo; and therefore thou and al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> who are in that nature, knows not what you ſpeak, and therefore none hath been at all profited by your Miniſtery; and bleſſed be the Lord that its hid from the eyes of the wiſe, and revealed to babes: and thy envious ſpirit is ſeen, that it is of thy father the Devil, who is the accuſer of the Brethren, that would lay a thing down as an error, and tels of daſhing in peices our principles, and yet knows not what it is, nor what we ſpeak; doſt thou accuſe, and knows not for what, let ſhame cover thy face, that ever thou ſhould put pen to paper, or ſpeak of God or Chriſt, and ſpeaks thou knows not what, and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n thou hath hatched a thing, and concludes there is nothing in man to be ſpoken to, but man, and before thou knew not, and ſo art in confuſion; for Chriſt and his Apoſtles always ſpoke to man, thou ſaith the Apoſtle ſaith, he went and miniſtered to the Spirits in priſon, and to open the blind eye, and to raiſe the dead, and the dead ſhould hear the voice of the Son of God and live, and he preached liberty to the captive, and is given for a covenant to open the blind eyes, and unſtop the deaf ears, and make the lame to walk, if thou haſt an ear thou may hear, but not to feed thy ſerpents wiſdom do I ſpeak, I will ſhut thee out, for into it thou cannot enter, but through death, and death wrote the book, and the Apoſtles were made manifeſt to every mans conſcience in the ſight of God; and the ſlothful ſervant had a talent given to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove, which was anothers and not his own, and that was required of him, and that will God require of man, and unto that we ſpeak which hears us, and ſhall witneſs us eternally, even that which is not in the tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion, neither is of man, but is given to man to improve, and ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is not far from man, but this is a myſterie, and it ſhall be ſealed for with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a parable ſpoke he not, to ſuch as thou art, and I know this is a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable; but in the end thou ſaith, thou knows not how they can ſpeak to any light in man diſtinct from him, unleſs they ſpeak unto Satan, or ſome of his legions: here again thy ſhame and ignorance is made mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, we ſpeak to the ear, and the eye in man, which the God of the world hath blinded, and this is not of man, and yet is not far from man, but diſtinct that is thy own word, I do not own it: bring forth the blind that hath eyes, and the deaf that hath ears; did the Prophets ſpeak to the devil in man; we ſpeak to the witneſs of God in man, and according to this ſhall all be judged, if thou haſt an ear thou may hear: oh thou blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemer, doſt thou call that which may be known of God, which is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:172154:4" rendition="simple:additions"/> on <hi>Rom.</hi> 2. doſt thou call this a Legion of Devils, even that which declares the eternal power and Godhead, but thou art he that calls the Maſter of the houſe <hi>Beelſibub,</hi> and in that nature thou art, and the Lord will rebuke.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Principle, That thou cals a miſtake, that is, the denying the uſe of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in the matters of God, calling it ſerpentine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The world by wiſdome knowes not God, and all the diſputing and twining, and laviſhing of the wiſdome of man, and that which thou cals reaſon, it is corrupted, and is ſhut out, and who lives in that nature, are the unreaſonable men that hath not faith: now he that hath not faith, hath not reaſon, and he that hath faith, hath the witneſs in himſelf, but I ſee thee, thy witneſs is without thee, and ſo thou ſpeaks unreaſonably; and all that would underſtand the myſteries of the Kingdome, muſt come through death, for light ſhines in darkneſs, but darkneſs cannot com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend it, and therefore one cryes loe here, and loe there, and with that which thou cals reaſon, is Scripture torn aſunder, and ſtrife, and conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and endleſs diſputes and ſtriving for Maſtery, which is carnal, and all this we deny: And thou ſaith upon this ground, they will not do as the Apoſtles and Chriſt himſelf, who diſputed with the gainſayers, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 6. and <hi>Stephen, Acts<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> 6. and thou brings in ſome of the Synagogue of Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines, and Syrenians, and Alexandrians, and the reſt, and diſputed with <hi>Stephen,</hi> and they were not able to reſiſt him: let many hundreds of this City of London, both in publike, and in private, bear witneſs againſt, if we have not diſputed, and hath not been ready to give an anſwer to the gainſayers, though not ſuch a one as they deſired, even as Chriſt our Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter did not anſwer the Iews in their ſubtil tempting of him, and of thoſe Sects that encountred both <hi>Stephen</hi> and <hi>Paul,</hi> truly I muſt needs ſay unto thee, we have met with the ſame generation in this City, whereof thou art one, and truly more ſubtil then they were, but in the eternal light you are all ſeen, and many though they could not gainſay, yet have reſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed us; and after a little, thou ſaith thou pleads not for carnal reaſon, for this will not ſuffer any to follow Chriſt: further, then they can carry their own things, their honours, pleaſures, eaſe and luſts, to that in thy conſcience I ſpeak, whether this doth not rule thee and guide thee; it will let thee ſee thou art pleading for honour, and reſpecting mens perſons, and hath them in admiration, becauſe of advantage, and brings the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of others to prove and uphold thy deceit, which they were neither commanded nor commended for to oppoſe the commands of Chriſt, and the expreſs Scripture: and thou goes on further and ſaith, God is the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of memory, and wiſdome, and reaſon; but I tell thee there is a wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and a reaſon that God will confound, for by faith we know the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens were made, and ſee them upholden, and by faith all things is brought to our remembrance, and it is the light that convinceth of ſin, even the light of Chriſt, and ſo in the eternal light I ſee what thou pleads for; for eating of the tree of knowledge, and there thou art till thou art become a fool, and die to that reaſon; thou ſhalt never eat of the tree of life, and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:172154:5"/> therefore fleſh be ſilent: and thou ſaith, thou doth not allow that reaſon that gets only a concluſion, or an argument inſtead of Chriſt; and after thou ſaith the day is yet to dawn, and the day ſtar to ariſe, and thou pryes violently for it: and here what hath thou more for an aſſurance of thy ſalvation, then an argument, and a concluſion inſtead of Chriſt, for thou confeſſes the day is not dawned, and then thou art yet in the night, and in darkneſs, for the day dawns, and the day ſtar ariſes before Chriſt be wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſed, but thou knows no ſuch thing, as either Chriſt, or the dawning, if thou had not others teſtimony, and that is without; and thou art one Chriſt ſpoke of ſince <hi>Iohn,</hi> the Kingdome ſuffers violence, and many thruſt into it, and thou art ſtriving, and art violent, but I ſay thou ſhalt not be able till thou lay down thy contending in thy carnal wiſdom, and ſtriving, and reſiſting, but thou muſt become a fool, and ſit at Ieſus feet, but thou art full, and rich, and hole, and need no Phyſitian, and therefore thou muſt be ſent empty away, and when the book of conſcience ſhall be opened, thou ſhalt be judged for what thou hath done againſt the innocent.</p>
            <p>Now ſomething in Anſwer to the fourth particular, Which thou ſayeſt is a tenent held forth by the Northern people; which is a denying of the aſſention, and being of the body of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> O thou enemy of righteouſneſs, when wilt thou ceaſe to pervert the right way of God, who uttereth thy lies and ſlanders againſt the Innocent God ſhall judge thee, and between thee and us, whether thou haſt not utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed lyes and falſe accuſations in the name of the Lord, and put forth in writing unto the world for truth, that which is abſolutely contrary unto the Truth; God will reward thee, thou full of ſubtilty, according to thy deeds who takes part with the Dragon againſt the Lamb, and goes about by thy lying ſlanders, to rend the way of truth (which thou canſt not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend in thy ſerpents wiſdome) odious unto all men, but God taketh our part againſt thee, and will daſh thy lyes and ſlanders, and thy Impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent forehead in pieces, even by that power which make the earth to quake and tremble, which is become a reproach unto this generation, many who have heard us ſince we came to this City (though our enemies) ſhall wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs againſt thee, and for us in this particular; for we have oft witneſſed forth, and I do here again witneſs forth in the ſight of God and men, that Chriſt Ieſus is riſen, and aſcended far above all principalities and powers, and the ſame which deſcended into the lower parts o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he earth, is alſo aſcended, and raigns over all, ſubjecting all unto him<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>lf, that he may be Lord over all, and in all, and may be glorified by all; and members of his body we are (who thou enviouſly rails againſt) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſſes of the body we are, whereof Chriſt Ieſus is head, and becauſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the dead body, which is aſcended, we are call<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> queſtion, and all Sects and opinions are troubled, and on an uproar <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> us; and I tell thee plainly, we are ſo far from denying the aſc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nſion and being of the body of Chriſt, that becauſe of being called to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>eſs i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, as being members of it, we are perſecuted and reviled by ſuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> thy ſelf, whoſe carnal conceptions and imaginations of truth we do deny, and doth teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:172154:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> unto you all, that though death is the reſurrection and aſcenſion wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſed, and every one that reads the Scripture is not witneſſes of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of the body of Chriſt; and all whoſe witneſs is onely without them, other mens words which had the witneſſe within them, we deny to be true witneſſes, but are found falſe witneſſes of the reſurrection, and of the aſcenſion, and knows not Chriſt, nor his body but by hearſay; and whereas thou brings many Scriptures to prove his reſurrection and aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion: I anſwer, the Scriptures we own to be a true declaration of the witneſſe which was in the Apoſtles, of the reſurrection, and of the aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Chriſt; but thee we deny, who art found a lyar, and a ſlanderer, and thy reſurrection will be unto condemnation, and thy aſcenſion will prove a deſcending into the bottomleſs pit, for ever to be tormented, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept thou repent, and from the life of the holy men of God thou art ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed out, who art found in the way of ungodlineſs, and thou haſt nothing to do to profeſs their words, who art out of their life, nor no inheritance in their words; but as thou ſeals them, adding thy own imaginations up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, and wreſting them to thy own deſtruction, being one unlearn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the way of God, and in the doctrine of Chriſt: And whereas thou ſayeſt, and thus you ſee how theſe men deny the Lord that bought them, if they deny the body that was crucified for them: I anſwer, We deny not the Lord that bought us, for by him can we ſay, we have received the end of his coming, and of his death and aſcenſion, even he hath purchaſed us, and ſet us free from the power and Kingdome of the Divel, of lyes and ſlanders, and falſe accuſations after us, by whom the Man-child is brought forth, and this ſhall ſtand for thy own condition, who art a wandring ſtar, and hath no habitation in the heavens; God will plead with thee, thou who haſt ſet thy ſelf againſt the Lord, in ſlandring and reviling his ſervants.</p>
            <p>Now to thy fift Particular, That we deny the Ordinances of Chriſt, in which thou ſayeſt, we alſo deny the Lord that bought us.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The way unto God, and unto everlaſting life, which is Chriſt Ieſus, we deny not, but are true witneſſes, that ſame Chriſt alone which was crucified at Ieruſalem, and which God hath raiſed from the dead, and which is aſcended, in him alone is ſalvation, and by him alſo alone are all juſtified that believe in him; and this we declare freely unto all people, that Chriſt is the Ordinance of God, ordained by him, for the ſalvation of all that believe, and for the condemnation of all that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve not in him; and that the way unto this Chriſt, is not any outward viſible thing, but even that which is manifeſted from him, leads up unto him, even the light by which he hath lightned every one that cometh into the world, which is ſpiritual as Chriſt is ſpiritual; and whereas thou ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, there is nothing that Chriſt commanded, but we deny it, mentioning onely your Baptiſm, and your Breaking of Bread, which is your Idol, and your Image you bow unto; the one Baptiſm, which is by one Spirit into one Body, into the death of Chriſt, we are witneſſes of, and the bread which we break, is the Communion of the body of Chriſt, and we
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:172154:6"/> being many, are one bread; but the beggerly rudiments of the world, we teſtifie againſt, being witneſſes of the ſubſtance, and your taken on pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices, in that nature, which is contrary unto Chriſt, from the words and commands of Chriſt, unto them that followed him, we alſo teſtifie againſt, and in it you are found among the Papiſts, which walks by tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, and not from the motion of the Spirit of God; and here thou art found a lyar, for the commands of Chriſt is our life, our joy, and our peace and glory, and hereby we know that we love him, becauſe we keep his commandments, and they are not grievous unto us (which is not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by tradition from without us, but by the eternal Spirit, Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus revealed in us, which is not contrary to his commands without, but a fulfilling of them; for he is not a Iew who is one outwardly, whoſe praiſe is of men, neither is the obedience which Chriſt doth require, a confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming the outward man unto an outward thing, which obedience is your boaſting onely, and there onely your difference lieth from all the world, in the outward appearance, Phariſee-like; but the ground of enmity, and ſeat of the beaſt, is ſtanding within, and you are twofold more the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the divel, and Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is riſen to confound you, and to break your Image to pieces, and he ſhall have the praiſe of God, who is the Iew in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, whoſe obedience and Circumciſion is inward, and who have no confidence in the fleſh: and whereas thou exhorts to hear one loving re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proof out of the Scripture, which their predeceſſors (I mean the Papiſts) thou ſayeſt would have taken from us in the Engliſh tongue, and theſe would take from us the vertue of i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, that is to ſay, the ſharpneſs and ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of it, by working upon us a diſlike to it; I anſwer, we do deny thy voice, and though thou may bring Scripture in thy mouth to us, it is but as the divel brought to Chriſt, and we deny it from thee, for if thou ſay God lives, thou ſwears falſely, and the Papiſts they are thy predeceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, who walks onely by tradition as thou doſt, from a thing without them, ſeparate from the life, and both them and thee we do deny, and bears witneſs againſt you, to be without God in the world, in the alie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation out of the Covenant, knowing nothing of him, but what you have heard by a fame and a report, and that we in the leaſt would take from any the vertue of the Scripture; it is a lye uttered by the divel in thee, for we teſtifie unto all, that it ſhall every tittle be fulfilled, even upon the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly, and thou ſhall know it one day to be fulfilled upon thee, thou lyar muſt be caſt into the lake that burns for ever; and this is the ſharpneſs and ſweetneſs which you muſt have from it, who art a falſe accuſer of the Brethren, bearing the Image of the Dragon, the Divel whoſe ſervant thou art, as it is manifeſt by thy writing, and this many will witneſs with us, that oft we do declare upon the juſt and the unjuſt, the Scripture muſt be fulfilled, and the righteous muſt have a reward, and the ungodly muſt have their portion in outer darkneſs, according as the Scripture ſaith and herein we eſtabliſh the Scripture in its place, to be a true declaration of God and Chriſt, and what the righteous and the wicked ſhall enjoy, but that it is God and Chriſt, or the way unto life, we deny it; for this is its
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:172154:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> vertue, a declaration of that which the Saints believed, and he that wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes the ſame life and truth which it teſtifies of, to be made manifeſt in him, is a witneſs of it, and it is a witneſs unto him, and this is the vertue of i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>; if thou haſt an ear thou may hear, and that we work upon any a diſlike of the Scriptures; I charge thee to be a lyar, for to the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filling and eſtabliſhing of it we declare, that every one may walk up in the life of it, by that which gave it forth, and to be a true witneſs of it, as they were that ſpoke it; but thee and all ſuch we do deny, which adds your imaginations upon it, to ſell for money; and whereas thou ſayeſt by way of Query to us, hath the Scripture no power over you? have you a ſpirit to guide you without a written word, it is out of Gods govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment if it cannot be brought to the Law and to the Teſtimony? I anſwer, Ieſus Chriſt onely hath power over us, and not a Letter without us; and the ſpirit by which we are guided, is no other but that which gave forth the Scripture, which ſpirit is the Word of God, and which ſpirit the Scripture bears witneſs unto; and this we often ſay, if we ſpeak or act contrary to the Scripture, let us be judged by the Scripture, and we, as <hi>Paul</hi> did, do commend all that ſhall ſearch the Scripture, to try whether theſe things be not ſo, which we declare; and herein we are under the government of God, who alone hath power over us; but you who hath not the ſame ſpirit which gave forth the Scripture, neither knows it, nor us, but out of the evil corrupt ground thou judges of it, as thou doſt of us, and both thy judgement of it and us, is to be judged by the eternal light of Chriſt, which never erreth nor changeth; and whereas thou ſayeſt, we may be fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar ſpirits for ought thou knoweſt, what muttering and uncouth howl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is among us, which you cannot but impute to be a ſpirit contrary to the Word, if we will not come to the Word to be tryed; I anſwer, it is true, thou knows us not, for we are unknow to thy generation, though you have the Scripture, which our life and practices, are witneſs of; as Chriſt was unknown to the Phariſees who had the Scripture, which he came to fulfil; and thou art ignorant of the Scripture, and a ſcorner of the power of it, who cals the power of the Lord uncouth howling; what would you have ſaid concerning <hi>David,</hi> who lay roaring all the day long, even as a man diſtracted; and concerning <hi>Habakkuk,</hi> whoſe belly trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, and whoſe lips quivered, when he heard the voice of God; but here you are made manifeſt, who ſcorns that which the Scripture bears witneſs of, and never knew what it was to be pricked to the heart, as they were which cryed out, what ſhall we do to be ſaved; and if thou canſt, thou may try by the Scripture, whether this be any other but that which the Scripture ſpeaks of, and not the ſame ſpirit which made the ſervants of God to quake and tremble, which the Scripture ſpeaks of, which this day is become a reproach, even unto them that profeſs the Scripture; for by the word of God, which the Scripture declares of, ſhall all fleſh trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and be confounded, and then thy ſelf ſhall be judged, into the lake that burns for ever, except thou repent; and whereas thou ſayeſt, how ſhall you do to try the ſpirits, if we deny both the written word which is
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:172154:7"/> your rule, and reaſon to; for we appeal from both.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Art thou not aſhamed to ſay the Scripture is thy rule, who art found a lyar, and a falſe accuſer; thy rule ſhall try thee, and ſhall bear witneſs againſt thee, when God judgeth thee by Je<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>us Chriſt; for neither by the Scripture, nor thy corrupt reaſon, canſt thou know the things of God, who art a natural man, in the fall, in the world without God; but again I ſay, let any try us, in our lives, and in our practices, and if we ſpeak, or act contrary to the Scripture, judge us by it; but thy eye is blinded, and when thou ſeeſt the Scripture fulfilled, even crying out as a woman in travel, thou cals it uncou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h howling, and a ſpirit contrary to the Scripture; and how art thou able to try, who art blind and deaf in the myſterie of the Kingdome of God, for thy reaſon muſt never enter unto God, but is ſhut out, and in ſeeing thou ſees not, and in hearing thou doſt not underſtand; and upon thee herein is the Scripture fulfilled: And whereas thou ſayeſt, we will not have Chriſt to rule over us, for we deny both his Perſon, and Word, which is the rule of life and love. I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, O thou lyar, God ſhall judge thee, let ſhame cover, and let thy own conſcence convince thee, for thy lies and ſlanders againſt the inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, Chriſt Ieſus is our head, and we are of his body, and his word is ſweet unto us, even our life, and rule of life, and by him we ſee thee to be an enemy to him, and from him I judge thee; not his word, but the ſpirit of the Divel is thy rule, for he is the ruler and father of lies and ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ars, and thy portion thou muſt have with him in the lake, and what thou ſayeſt of us, it ſhall ſtand for thy own condition, thou wilt not have Chriſt to rule over thee; who lives in thy luſt and carnal mind without the fear of God, which Chriſt comes to deſtroy, in all that witneſs him: and whereas thou ſayeſt, in the name of God thou proclaims, that thoſe men that diſown the written Word, are not ſpiritual men, they may have the ſpirit of Antichriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Thou haſt nothing to proclaim from God, but as the falſe Prophets, had other men words, and alſo I ſay, if thou find any that diſown the Scripture, we alſo diſown ſuch, and do ſay they are not ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual men, but hath the ſpirit of Antichriſt; and of this number thou art, guided by the ſpirit of Antichriſt, who art a lyar and a falſe accuſer which is contrary to the ſpirit of Chriſt, and art without faith, and ſo art unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable in the corrupt reaſon, without pure and undefiled reaſon: and whereas thou ſayeſt, who but the ſpirit of Antichriſt durſt countermand the commands of our Law-giver the Lord Ieſus. Chriſt? I anſwer, the commands of Chriſt is ſpiritual, and in and by the ſpirit, and not tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional from the Letter without, and Antichriſt m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y conform to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand without, as the Phariſees did, and yet be an enemy to the life and ſubſtance of his commands; and this is thy own condition as it was the Phariſees, who ſaid he deſtroyed the Law, which came to fulfil it, as thou ſayeſt we make void and deny the commands of Chriſt, when as we are witneſſes of them, and directs all into the fulfilling of them; and thy
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:172154:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſpirit here is tryed to be the ſpirit of Antichriſt, the ſame which was in them that perſecuted Chriſt, and thou rails and ſlanders his members: and whereas thou ſayeſt, there were never any men appeared in the world ſo like thoſe that <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaketh of in his ſecond Epiſtle, and theſe deſire to overthrow the writings of the ſpirit of God: I anſwer, <hi>Peter</hi> ſpoke of ſuch as thou art, for a cloud carried about wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h the Tempeſt thou art, and a Well without water, and defiles the fleſh, and diſpiſes the Saints digni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y, and ſpeaking great ſwelling words of vanity, while thou thy ſelf art a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant of corruption, ſerving the Devil, by lying, and falſely accuſing, and that we deſire to overthrow the writings of the Spi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>it of God; thou art a lyar, for we go about to eſtabl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſh it, and declares of him, who is the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of it, and God will reward thee according to thy deeds, who alſo accuſes us of unſeemly kiſſing in Glaſiers-Hall, thou ſayeſt if Mr. <hi>Pope</hi> do not belye us; I anſwer, this is another lye, which proceeds from thee, let all the honeſt hearted which ever hath frequented our aſſembly at that place teſtifie againſt thee, and Mr. <hi>Pope,</hi> and your father the Divel, whom by lying you ſerve, and that no unſeemly actions have proceeded from us, but ſoberneſs and civility; and unſeemly actions ſhall ſtand for thy own condition, they are ſuch as thy ſelf, who commits unſeemly brawling, and folly and vain contending againſt the truth in Glaſiers hall, as many honeſt hearted will witneſs againſt you, and for us who have ſeen your baſe actions, as ſcorning and flowting in that place; and ſo here you your ſelves are guilty of the wantonneſs which <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaks of, and of aluring through the luſts of the fleſh, which thou ſlanderouſly would caſt upon us; and thou further ſayeſt, none ever premiſed to themſelves ſo much liberty as theſe and the Ranters, in being freed from the power and tryal of the Word. I anſwer, both the Ranters and thee we do abſolutely deny, and te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie againſt you both, to be in the enmity againſt God, and againſt us who are his ſervants: thou before was ranking us with the Papiſts, and now among the Ranters, but herein the Scripture is fulfilled upon us, as they h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ve done unto Chriſt, ſo they do unto us; he was numbered among tranſgreſſors by thy generation of painted Sepulchers, and whited walles, as we are by thee; and all liberty which is of the fleſh, and to the fleſh, we do deny, as many can witneſs, who are witneſſes of our Miniſtery; and again I ſay, he that is able, let him try us by the Scripture; but thou art blind, and hath hardened thy heart againſt God, and hath neither ſalt nor ſavory, and ſo is good for nothing but to be trodden under foot.</p>
            <p>And wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>reas thou ſayeſt, the Lord bleſs every one of his from the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of <hi>Chandler,</hi> who formerly was the head of a Company of <hi>Shakers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I anſwer, The day is coming when thou canſt not fly the wrath of God, though thou pray God will not hear thee, and if ever thou haſt ſeen <hi>Chandler</hi> in this condition, thou might have read thy figure in him, weep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ng and gnaſhing of teeth will be thy portion for ever; and I ſay unto the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>is condi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of <hi>Chandlers</hi> is not come up<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n him, becauſe he w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ce a <hi>Sh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> by the d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d of the Lord upon him, but becauſe he went out from that condition, out of the fear of God into the libe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ty of the fleſh, out of his ſhaking and fearing ſtate which once he was in, and this
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:172154:8"/> he ſhall witneſs with me to be true, and againſt thee, who would reproach the way of truth by him, when the book of conſcience is opened.</p>
            <p>And whereas thou further ſayeſt, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ir ſpirit w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>l perſwade them that they are not fallen from righteouſneſſe, and would therefore juſtifie them.</p>
            <p>I anſwer, We are gathered up into righteouſneſs, and fallen from vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and this the Spirit of God perſwades us, and witneſſeth in us and for us, by which onely we are juſtified freely, and not by the works of the law, nor by any outward obſervance; and herein thou alſo art a lyar; who ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ith, we are fallen from righteouſneſs, for even the righteouſneſs of God is manifeſted to us, by which we deny all your carnal outward obſervances, by which you think to obtain life and righteouſneſs.</p>
            <p>Now in anſwer to thy ſixt Particular, which thou calls a heavy and ſad offence, which is a denying honour to men, which thou ſaiſt is the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of good men; to which <hi>I</hi> doe anſwer: God hath commanded to h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nour him alone, and not to bow down to any Creature, and thou h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt brought m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ny Scriptures to oppoſe the command of God, and ſo art more fully made manifeſt to be an enemy unto him, which would plead againſt him, by that which is written from him, pleading the example of good men; which is no example to us to break the command of God, no more then <hi>Davids</hi> example in committing whoredom, and <hi>Ioſephs</hi> example in ſwearing by the life of <hi>Pharoah,</hi> is an example for any to act thoſe things now; and I do utterly deny that any of theſe Scriptures which thou haſt cited, will prove and maintain your heatheniſh cuſtome, in your deceitfull way of honouring one another, to pleaſe the divel in one another, which is without the fear of God; and it is a ſad offence to none but the divel, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it weakens and diſturbs his kingdome, of which thou art, as is made manifeſt, who pleads to uphold it from the Scripture; but vain honour with flattering titles unto any man we do deny, but yet we honour all men in the Lord, and out of him we honour none, to uphold the pride of man, for God will bring it all down, and lay it in the duſt, and exalt himſelf, to reign over you all; and whereas thou ſayeſt, how far are theſe men from the holy Writt: To which I ſay and anſwer, thou ſlanderouſly would make us to appear odious in the ſight of men, but all the upright in heart will ſee thee, and thy blindneſs and ignorance, who brings that Scripture where Chriſt (in fulfilling the Law of God, which he came to fulfil) wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped in the Temple, to prove and maintain the worſhip of man.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> O you blind Phariſee and perverter of the Scripture, God will plague thee, thou enemy of his truth, who perverts the Scripture, to thy own deſtruction, and art worſe then the Phariſees, who ſaid he reſpected no mans perſon, and they ſhall witneſs againſt thee; and whereas thou ſpeaks of honouring father and mother, which thou ſayeſt we deny in this our pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice: I anſwer, I charge thee to be a lyar, for as I ſaid we honour all men in the Lord, and directs all children and ſervants, to obey their parents and maſters in the Lord, and this m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ny can witneſs for us, which have more frequented our aſſemblies then thou haſt done; but this we alſo te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie, where the obedience to any man ſtands in oppoſition to God, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to God is rather to be choſen; and herein he that will not hate father
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:172154:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> or mother for Chriſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſake is not worthy of him; but thou carnal, earthly man, is pleading for the Kingdome of the Divel, to honour man above God; and I ſay how can you believe that ſeeks honour one of another, your honour and your heatheniſh cuſtome we teſtifie againſt, yet unto e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very ordinance of man we are ſubject for conſcience ſake.</p>
            <p>Now to that which you call the ſeventh miſtake, affording abſolute per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection at one Inſtant, in admitting of none but perfect men into conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> It is a miſtake in thee, for ſuch a word never proceeded fr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m us, I may ſay it is rather an abſolute lye invented by thee, to make us odious, then a miſtake from us; for thy heart is deſperately wicked, and thy torment is kindling by the breath of the Almigh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y; many which have heard us will teſtifie againſt thee, for we ſay the Saints have their growth up into a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect man in Chriſt, as Chriſt himſelf had, and we ſay alſo their is chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren and young men and fathers, as the Apoſtle ſaid, but thou art not aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to utter thy lies and ſlanders, which hundreds in this Ci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y will wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs againſt thee for a lyar; and even thy light in thy conſcience will accuſe thee to thy face, that thou haſt imagined lyes and miſchief upon thy bed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us; and whereas thou brings many Scriptures to prove thy ſlanders againſt us to be true: to which I anſwer, all the Scriptures we own and bear witneſs unto, by that ſpirit from which they were ſpoken; but thee and thy ſpirit we deny, for both you and it is of the divel; and thou haſt dive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhly added thy imagina<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ions upon them, and wreſted them, which I ſhall not now mention, becauſe I do deny the thing which thou aſſerteſt to be an abſolute lie, and do ſay unto thee, God will reward thee thou ſlande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous tongue: and whereas further thou ſayeſt, in our perfection we deny any man being under frailty or capablen ſs to ſin to be of our communion. I anſwer, here again thou art a lyar, theſe words war never uttered by us, as thou haſt ſet them down; but I ſay, he that ſins is of the divel, and ſuch we have no unity withal, nor ſuch hath no unity with God, for no impure thing enters to him, nor hath communion with him; for whoſoever works abomination, is to be caſt out, and trodden in the winepreſs of his wrath, where the portion of lyars is, among whom thou muſt reeeive thy reward; for with ſuch we have no union, who are diſobedient children, but with him who in the leaſt meaſure which he hath received from God, walks up in the light unto God, we have unity and communion with him; thou ſayeſt one of us told <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hee (that which ſinned could not be ſaved.) I anſwer, it is out of the reach of thy wiſdome, and thy vultero<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s eye ſhall never ſee it; I ſay as the Scripture ſaith, the ſoul that ſinneth muſt die, and every man muſt die for his own iniquity, if thou haſt an ear thou mayeſt hear; and fu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ther thou ſayeſt, that our doctrine may appear to be utterly againſt the Scripture; thou brings <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.23. where <hi>Paul</hi> was under the Law, and ſaw a Law in the members, warring againſt the Law of the mind: I anſwer, this Scripture we own, and are true witneſſes of it; but there was alſo a time, that the Law of the ſpirit of li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, had freed him from the Law of ſin and death; but thy ignorance is made manifeſt, who brings one Scripture to opp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe another, and knows not the conditions in thy ſelf, from which <hi>Paul</hi> ſpoke, and ſo art ignorant of what he ſpoke; for I ſay,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:172154:9"/> there is a time without the Law, and a time under the Law, and a time dead to the Law, and not under it, and all theſe ſtates <hi>Paul</hi> witneſſed, which we alſo in our meaſure are witneſſes of, which thou knowes not in thy ſelf, and ſo wreſts <hi>Pauls</hi> words: And whereas thou ſayeſt, yet let not them think that we by this doctrine nouriſh ſin, having brought many Scriptures to plead for ſin; I anſwer, being guilty in thy ſelf, thou art afraid, and hath a jealouſie leſt we ſhould lay it to thy charge; and truly concerning thee we think nothing in this matter, for thy heart and the ſecrets of it is made manifeſt in the eternall light, by which thou art comprehended, and anſwered, and by which God will eternall judge thee; therefore repent leſt the wrath of God overtake thee, and thou be ſwept away with the beſom of deſtruction, who hath falſly accuſed and ſlandered us with lies and falſe reproaches: but now its the time that <hi>Pilate</hi> and <hi>Herod</hi> is made friends, and <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog</hi> is gathered together to battel, to compaſs the Camp of the Saints about; and even the Prieſts and their crew, and the <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts</hi> and their crew, and all Sects is combined againſt the truth, but God is with us, and in him alone can we rejoyce over you all for ever and ever; and in him make our boaſt all the day long, for this is our heritage, every tongue that riſeth up in judgement againſt us ſhall be condemned, for the Lord is our port, and even the ſtone which is refuſed is become the head ſtone of the corner, and thou <hi>Howet</hi> ſhall be grinded to powder by it, who hath bent thy bow to ſhoot at the righteous, therefore conſider what thou haſt done, and repent, leſt God tear thee in pieces, and there be none to deliver.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:172154:10"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
